Chapter 26.
Knights and squires.
The chief mate of the Peak Quad was Starbucks, a native of Nantucket and a
Quaker by descent. He was a long, earnest man, and though born on an icy
coast, seemed well adapted to endure the hot latitudes, his flesh being hard as
twice baked biscuit. Transported to the Indies, his live blood would not spoil
like bottled ale. He must have been born in some time of general drought and
famine, or upon one of those fast days for which his state is famous. Only some
30 arid summers had he seen. Those summers had dried up all his physical superfluousness,
but this his thinness, so to speak, seemed no more the token of wasting
anxieties and cares, then it seemed the indication of any bodily blight. It was
merely the condensation of the man. He was by no means ill-looking, quite the
contrary. His pure tight skin was an excellent fit, and closely wrapped up in
it, and imbalmed with inner health and strength like a revivified Egyptian,
this Starbucks seemed prepared to endure for long ages to come, and to endure
always, as now, for be it polar snow or torid sun, like a patent chronometer,
his interior vitality was warranted to do well in all climates. Looking into
his eyes, you seem to see there the yet lingering images of those thousandfold
perils he had calmly confronted through life. A stayed, steadfast man, whose
life, for the most part, was a telling pantoime of action, and not a tame
chapter of sounds. Yet, for all his hearty sobriety and fortitude, there
were certain qualities in him which at times affected, and in some cases seemed
well nigh to overbalance all the rest.
uncommonly conscientious for a seaman and endued with a deep natural reverence
the wild watery loneliness of his life did therefore strongly incline him to
superstition but to that sort of superstition which in some organizations
seems rather to spring somehow from intelligence than from ignorance outward
portance and inward presentiments were his and if at times these things bent
the welded iron of his soul so much more did his faraway domestic memory Memories
of his young Cape wife and child tend to bend him still more from the original
ruggedness of his nature, and open him still further to those latent influences
which, in some honestarted men, restrain the gush of daredevil daring so often
against by others in the more perilous vicissitudes of the fisheries. I will
have no man in my boat, said Starbucks, who is not afraid of a whale. By this he
seemed to mean not only that the most reliable and useful courage was that
which arises from the fair estimation of the encountered peril, but that an
utterly fearless man is a far more dangerous comrade than a coward.
I I said Stub the second mate Starbucks there is as careful a man as you'll find
anywhere in this fishery. But we shall heong see what that word careful
precisely means when used by a man like Stub or almost any other whale hunter.
Starbucks was no crusader after perils.
In him courage was not a sentiment but a thing simply useful to him and always at
hand upon all mortally practical occasions. Besides, he thought perhaps
that in this business of whailing, courage was one of the great staple
outfits of the ship, like her beef and her bread, and not to be foolishly
wasted. Therefore, he had no fancy for lowering for whales after sundown, nor
for persisting in fighting a fish that too much persisted in fighting him. Four
thought Starbucks, I am here in this critical ocean to kill whales for my
living and not to be killed by them for theirs. And that hundreds of men had
been so killed. Starbucks well knew.
What doom was his own fathers? Where in the bottomless deeps could he find the
torn limbs of his brother. with memories like these in him, and moreover given to
a certain superstitiousness, as has been said, the courage of this Starbucks,
which could nevertheless still flourish, must indeed have been extreme. But it
was not in reasonable nature that a man so organized, and with such terrible
experiences and remembrances as he had, it was not in nature that these things
should fail in latently engendering an element in him which, under suitable
circumstances, would break out from its confinement, and burn all his courage
up. and brave as he might be. It was that sort of bravery chiefly visible in
some intrepid men, which while generally abiding firm in the conflict with seas
or winds or whales or any of the ordinary irrational horrors of the
world, yet cannot withstand those more terrific because more spiritual terrors
which sometimes menace you from the concentrating brow of an enraged and mighty man.
But were the coming narrative to reveal in any instance the complete abasement
of poor Starbucks fortitude, scarce might I have the heart to write it, for
it is a thing most sorrowful, nay shocking, to expose the fall of valor in
the soul. Men may seem detestable as joint stock companies and nations,
naves, fools, and murderers there may be. Men may have mean and meager faces,
but man in the ideal is so noble and so sparkling, such a grand and glowing
creature that over any ignaminious blemish in him all his fellows should
run to throw their costliest robes. That immaculate manliness we feel within
ourselves, so far within us that it remains intact, though all the outer
characters seem gone, bleeds with keenest anguish at the undraped
spectacle of a valor ruined man. Nor can piety itself at such a shameful sight
completely stifle her upbridings against the permitting stars. But this august
dignity I treat of is not the dignity of kings and robes, but that abounding
dignity which has no robed investature.
Thou shalt see it shining in the arm that wields a pick or drives a spike.
That democratic dignity which on all hands radiates without end from God
himself, the great God absolute, the center and circumference of all
democracy, his omnipresence, our divine equality.
If then to meanest mariners and renegades and castaways, I shall
hereafter ascribe high qualities, though dark, weave round them tragic graces, if
even the most mournful, per chance the most abased among them all, shall at
times lift himself to the exalted mounts. If I shall touch that workman's
arm with some ethereal light, if I shall spread a rainbow over his disastrous set
of sun, then against all mortal critics, bear me out in it, thou just spirit of
equality, which has spread one royal mantle of humanity over all my kind.
Bear me out in it, thou great democratic god, who dit not refuse the swart
convict Bunan, the pale poetic pearl.
Thou who dit clothed with doubly hammered leaves of finest gold the
stumped and poppered arm of old cervantes. Thou who dit pick up Andrew
Jackson from the pebbles. Who dst hurl him upon a warhorse. Who d thunder him
higher than a throne. Thou who in all thy mighty earthly marchings ever
culllest thy selectest champions from the kingly commons. Bear me out in it, oh God.